<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="31"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Contents











                                                                                                            •   What is pollution?


                                                                                                            •   What pollution can affect

                                                                                                            •   How pollution affects a company

                                                                                                            •   Why pollution affects a company


                                                                                                            •   Why we need to protect water

                                                                                                            •   Who is ultimately responsible?

                                                                                                            •   Common Offences


                                                                                                            •   Fines and Penalties

                                                                                                            •   Environmental Sentencing Guidelines

                                                                                                            •   In Court


                                                                                                            •   Disposal Options

                                                                                                            •   How clean is clean









               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[What is Pollution?







         •   Pollution is the introduction of contaminants into the
             natural environment that cause adverse change.



         •   It can take the form of chemical substances or energy,
             such as noise, heat or light.


         •   The components of pollution can be foreign substances
             and energies or naturally occurring contaminants.























                                                                                                       In simple terms, pollution is…
                                                                                                       …to much of the wrong thing in the wrong place








               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[What can pollution affect?







         •      People

         •      Buildings
         •      Air
         •      Water

         •      Soil






























           Receptor:

           Something that could be adversely affected by pollution





               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[How pollution affects a company







         •      Project risks and programme delays


         •      Fines and criminal sanctions
                                                                      The mis-management of a company’s operational activities can have a
         •      Brand damage                                          significant, detrimental impact on the quality of inland waterways.





                                                                      A successful company manages their operations to ensure that the risk
                                                                      associated with water pollution is minimised, allowing them to operate in a
                                                                      cost-effective way, successfully and profitably.





                                                                      A company who fails to plan for excess surface water and/or groundwater
                                                                      that it generates, can suffer harm to their business







                                                                      “Court Fines Weetabix £140,000 for polluting a river near factory”


                                                                      The Guardian 22             nd  November 2019









               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Why we need to protect water







         Pollution can kill fish and affect users such as farmers, industry and drinking water abstractions.



               EA State of the environment Feb 2018


               Key findings
               •  In 2016, 86% of river water bodies had not reached good ecological status. The main reasons for this is agriculture and rural land management,
                 the water industry, urban and transport pressures.


               • For assessed river water bodies in England, 55% were at less than good status for phosphorus in 2016.

               • Nearly half of groundwater bodies will not reach good chemical status by 2021. For groundwater protected for drinking, nitrate levels were
                 responsible for 65% of failures to achieve good chemical status.





                                                                        Valuing the Environment


                                                                        •       Annual sale of rod licenses in England - £1.4 million (Environment Agency)


                                                                        •       Coastal footpath adds £32 million to Welsh economy (BBC 2013)

                                                                        •       The total number of people in tourism jobs is estimated at 64,940, around 20%
                                                                                of the county’s total employment (Cumbria Tourism 2018)









               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Water is legally protected







         Controlled Waters




         As defined in Section 104 of the Water Resources Act 1991, as those waters which the Environment Agency and Natural Resources
         Wales has a duty to protect.


         The definition of controlled water is wide and includes:



                Relevant territorial waters: that part of territorial waters which extends three nautical miles seaward from the base
                lines, from which the breadth of the territorial sea is measured.




                Coastal waters: waters landward of the base lines to the high-water limit and the freshwater limits of any rivers.


                Inland freshwater: any river or watercourse above the freshwater limit and any lake or pond that discharges directly or

                indirectly into such a watercourse.


         These definitions include groundwater, as this is part of the water cycle and is interconnected with the surface water system






         Surface Water and Groundwater have legal protection.  It is an offence to pollute them.






               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Who owns pollution?







         Rylands v Fletcher (1866)



         Lancashire mill owner sued when water escaped from his mill pond and flooded a local mine.



         “A person who for his own purposes brings onto his lands and collects and keeps there, anything likely to do
         mischief if it escapes must keep it at his peril…



         ...is prima facie answerable for the damages resulting from its escape even if he has taken the utmost care to

         protect it from escaping”.
                                                                                                                                                               (Blackburn J)



         Lessons Learnt


         1.     Liability does not depend on proof of carelessness,  strict liability will apply.


         2.     We have a duty to ensure that anything we release into the environment will not

                cause harm to the environment.

         3.     The polluter will pay for the costs associated with his actions.









               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Who is ultimately responsible?







         Responsibility for preventing pollution rests with those in control of the site.





         The overriding guiding principle behind UK Environmental Legislation is that the



                Polluter Pays



         For construction sites this generally means



                The Main Contractor



         Everyone on site, including sub-contractors, must carry out their activities in line with plans,
         procedures and method statements designed to prevent pollution.







         Pollution prevention is a company wide responsibility












               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Common offences







         Pollution offences



         To Cause


         •      No need to prove that the defendant committed the offence
                with knowledge, the fact that he did it is sufficient knowledge


         •      Defendant does not need to be negligent in any way


         To knowingly permit



         •      Meaning a failure to prevent pollution, where the defendant
                had knowledge of the pollution



         Permitting Offences



         •       Make a discharge into the environment within out a permit being in place

         •       Contravene a permit or its conditions


         •       Make false entries in a register


         •       Falsify documents, etc



               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Fines penalties and sanctions







         Enforcement Undertakings


         •      An alternative to criminal proceedings


         •      Voluntary agreements


         •      The defendant agrees to pay compensation for the
                environmental damage caused and those he has affected





                                                                                                                 Criminal Proceedings



                                                                                                                 •      Fines and/or prison sentence
                                                                                                                 •      Magistrates Court and Crown Courts
                                                                                                                 •      Environmental Sentencing Guidelines


                                                                                                                 Other



                                                                                                                 •      Stop Notice

                                                                                                                 •      Prohibition Notice
                                                                                                                 •      Variation Order
                                                                                                                 •      Cost Recovery




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Enforcement undertaking
















































                                                                                                     North Sea Discoloured at Newtonhill

                                                                                                     (Credit Julia Fleming)






               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Environmental sentencing guidelines







         Aim



         •      To address the need for improved guidance
         •      Remove inconsistencies in sentencing
         •      Allow for fines that reflect the level of seriousness of the incident and degree of culpability of the defendant

         •      To recover any monetary benefit that the defendant may have gained by committing the offence


         Court Consideration



         •   Culpability
         •   Harm Factors
         •   Financial Standing of the defendant



         General rules to setting the level of a fine



         •    The more culpable the action the bigger the fine
         •    The greater the harm to the environment the bigger the fine
         •    The bigger the company the bigger the fine











               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Category 1 incident







                                                                Deliberate                  Reckless                   Negligent            Low/No Culpability


                               Large
                               Starting Point                   £1,000,000                  £550,000                   £300,000                    £50,000


                               Range                           £450,000 to                £250,000 to                 £140,000 to                £25,000 to
                                                                £3,000,000                 £1,500,000                  £750,000                   £130,000


                               Medium
                               Starting Point                    £400,000                   £220,000                   £120,000                    £20,000


                               Range                           £170,000 to                £100,000 to                 £55,000 to                 £10,000 to
                                                                £1,000,000                  £500,000                   £300,000                    £50,000


                               Small
                               Starting Point                    £100,000                    £55,000                    £30,000                     £5,000

                               Range                            £45,000 to                 £24,000 to                 £13,000 to                  £2,500 to
                                                                 £400,000                   £220,000                   £120,000                    £20,000



                               Micro
                               Starting Point                    £50,000                     £30,000                    £15,000                     £2,500

                               Range                             £9,000 to                  £3,000 to                  £1,500 to                   £500 to
                                                                  £95,000                    £55,000                    £30,000                     £5,000




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Category 2 incident







                                                                Deliberate                  Reckless                   Negligent            Low/No Culpability


                               Large
                               Starting Point                    £500,000                   £250,000                   £140,000                    £25,000


                               Range                           £180,000 to                £100,000 to                 £60,000 to                 £14,000 to
                                                                £1,250,000                  £650,000                   £350,000                    £70,000


                               Medium
                               Starting Point                    £170,000                   £100,000                    £55,000                    £10,000


                               Range                            £70,000 to                 £40,000 to                 £25,000 to                  £5,500 to
                                                                 £450,000                   £250,000                   £140,000                    £25,000


                               Small
                               Starting Point                    £45,000                     £24,000                    £13,000                     £2,500

                               Range                            £17,000 to                 £10,000 to                  £6,000 to                  £1,000 to
                                                                 £170,000                   £100,000                    £55,000                    £10,000



                               Micro
                               Starting Point                    £22,000                     £12,000                    £6,500                      £1,000

                               Range                             £3,000 to                  £1,500 to                  £1,000 to                   £350 to
                                                                  £45,000                    £24,000                    £13,000                     £2,400




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Category 3 Incident







                                                                Deliberate                  Reckless                   Negligent            Low/No Culpability


                               Large
                               Starting Point                    £180,000                   £100,000                    £60,000                    £14,000


                               Range                           £100,000 to                 £60,000 to                 £35,000 to                 £10,000 to
                                                                 £450,000                   £250,000                   £150,000                    £40,000


                               Medium
                               Starting Point                    £70,000                     £40,000                    £25,000                     £5,000


                               Range                            £40,000 to                 £24,000 to                 £24,000 to                  £3,500 to
                                                                 £180,000                   £100,000                    £60,000                    £14,000



                               Small
                               Starting Point                    £17,000                     £10,000                    £6,000                      £1,000

                               Range                            £10000 to                   £5,000 to                  £3,000 to                   £700 to
                                                                  £70,000                    £40,000                    £23,000                     £5,000



                               Micro
                               Starting Point                     £9,000                     £5,000                     £2,500                       £400


                               Range                             £2,000 to                  £1,000 to                   £500 to                    £175 to
                                                                  £17,000                    £10,000                     £5,500                     £1,000




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Category 4 incident







                                                                Deliberate                  Reckless                   Negligent            Low/No Culpability

                               Large
                               Starting Point                    £100,000                    £60,000                    £35,000                    £10,000


                               Range                            £55,000 to                 £35,000 to                 £22,000 to                  £7,000 to
                                                                 £250,000                   £160,000                   £100,000                    £25,000


                               Medium
                               Starting Point                    £40,000                     £24,000                    £14,000                     £3,000


                               Range                            £22,000 to                 £14,000 to                  £8,000 to                  £2,500 to
                                                                 £100,000                    £60,000                    £35,000                    £10,000



                               Small
                               Starting Point                    £10,000                     £5,000                     £3,000                       £700

                               Range                             £5,000 to                  £3,000 to                  £1,500 to                   £400 to
                                                                  £40,000                    £24,000                    £14,000                     £3,500



                               Micro
                               Starting Point                     £5,000                     £3,000                     £1,400                       £200


                               Range                             £1,000 to                   £500 to                    £350 to                    £100 to
                                                                  £10,000                    £5,500                      £3,000                      £700




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Is the sub-contractor hired help?







         November 2013



         National house builder and groundworker discharge sediment rich waters.





         Background



         •    The site experienced a period of heavy rainfall

         •    Straw bales blocking the outlet from a sediment lagoon were removed to
              reduce the risk of the site flooding


         •    Following removal of straw bales silty water was discharged from a
              settlement lagoon

         •    A member of the public reported that the local stream had become                                               Fines
              discoloured


                                                                                                                             •   Housebuilder £100,000



                                                                                                                             •   Groundworker £9,000








               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[18 month works program (25 minutes of pollution)







         Background                                                                                       In Mitigation





         •      Single pollution incident involving the release of                                        •      It was stated that this was an isolated incident of 25
                silt laden water into a tributary of the River Rother                                            minutes during an 18 month contract and the
                in Burwash                                                                                       company was of previous good character


         •      The EA discovered a brown discharge
                downstream of the works after a member of the
                public reported the discoloured water


         •      Further investigation showed that the river was
                visually and locally impacted on a temporary
                basis


         •      There was no evidence that local wildlife was
                adversely affected









                                                                                                                 Fine    £54,000
                                                                                                                 Costs  £5,955




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[Appeal court upholds £250,000 fine







         Background                                                                                           Sentencing Guidelines


         •      Blockage of sewage pumps caused a non-emergency                                               Large Company
                discharge of sewage into a brook and nearby

                conservation area                                                                                    o    Starting Point £60,000

         •      The utility company did not promptly respond to the                                                  o    Range £35,000 to £150,000
                alarms, allowing sewage to be discharged


                                                                                                              Court of Appeal

         Court Concluded                                                                                      “To bring the message home to the directors and

                                                                                                              shareholders of the organisation which has offended
         •   Pollution Level upper end of Category 3                                                          negligently more than once before, a substantial

         •   Level of Culpability = Negligence                                                                increase in the level of fines, sufficient to have a
                                                                                                              material impact on the finances of the company as a

                                                                                                              whole will ordinarily be appropriate”.

                                                                                                              “This may result in fines measured in millions of pounds”

                                                                                                               Total Fine £250,000











               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Disposal options











                                                  Off-Site                                             Foul Sewer



                                                Disposal








                                                                              Options












                                        Surface Water                                              Groundwater

















               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Off site disposal







         Duty of Care for Waste Disposal



         All parties in the Waste Disposal Chain have a responsibility to take reasonable measures to ensure that the water/waste:



                •    Is not disposed of unlawfully



                •    Is not disposed of in a manner likely to cause

                       o     pollution of the environment
                       o     harm to human health


                •    Does not escape



                •    Is transferred to an authorised person



                •    Is adequately described



                •    A written description is transferred with the waste



           How is a waste defined?






               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Discharge to foul sewer







         •      Regulated by the utility company that is responsible for the sewers and the operation of the sewage-treatment works
                through which the effluent will pass


         •      Such companies are designated as Water and Sewerage Undertakers and have powers to consent to discharge under the
                Water Industry Act 1991

         •      They will set limits on the content of the discharge so it will not harm:
                       o      Sewage Treatment process                                                                        You have to pay to use the Sewer
                       o      People who work in the sewage system
                       o      Sewage system itself                                                                            The more concentrated the effluent the
                                                                                                                              higher the charge
         •      Common consented conditions:

                       o    Flow Rate                                                                                         Even dilute effluents will be subjected to a
                       o    Daily Volume                                                                                      charge
                       o    Time of Discharge
                       o    Temperature                                                                                       Dilution will not reduce the overall costs
                       o    pH
                       o    Toxic Metals                                                                                      Cost calculated using the Modgen
                       o    Suspended Solids                                                                                  Formula
                       o    Ammonia
                       o    Sampling and Monitoring                                                                                    Cost = Volume x Strength

                       o    Chemical Oxygen Demand (COD)

                No flammable substances are permitted to be discharged




               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Discharge to the environment







         When do you need a permit?

         The discharge of contaminated liquids into Controlled Waters (Surface Water or

         Groundwater) is covered by the Environmental Permitting Regulations 2010


         You do not need a permit:


         •   to discharge uncontaminated water, for example, clean rainwater from
             roofs or small areas of hardstanding to surface water

         •   to discharge uncontaminated water collected from public roads and small
             parking areas, that’s been through a maintained oil separator or
             sustainable urban drainage system, to surface water

         •   for certain low-risk groundwater activities, known as groundwater activity
             exclusions

         •   if the discharge is made under a formal exemption



         Types of Permits                                                                                                     Permits take a minimum


         •   Standard                                                                                                         of 6 months to obtain

         •   Bespoke







               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Regulatory position statements







         What is a Regulatory Position Statement (RPS)




         •      It is a statement from the Environment Agency (EA) defining circumstances under which they will not prosecute
                you for not having a permit in place



         Temporary Dewatering from excavations to surface water



         You do not need a permit if you:

         •   Have a short term, temporary discharge of uncontaminated water which is wholly or mainly rainwater, from an
             excavation to surface water (such as pumping water out of an excavation on a building site)




         •   Comply with all the conditions in this regulatory position statement (RPS).







             This RPS does not cover the


             discharge to groundwater.








               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Temporary de-watering from excavations to


         surface water (1)





         Conditions you must comply with:






         The discharge must:

                •    be clean water, for example clear rainwater or infiltrated groundwater
                     which has collected in the bottom of temporary excavations


                •    not result in water containing fine or coarse suspended solids (silty water)
                     entering surface water

                •    not last more than 3 consecutive months (the activity may stop and
                     restart but the clock does not restart) - if the activity is likely to go over 3

                     consecutive months then you need to apply for a permit

                •    be made to surface water, such as a river, stream or the sea

                •    have a method statement that minimises the risk of pollution

















               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Temporary de-watering from excavations to


         surface water (2)





         The discharge must not:






         •   pollute surface water

         •   contain any chemical dosing agents, flocculants or coagulants


         •   be from a site which is contaminated by oil, metals, hydrocarbons,
             solvents or pesticides or other polluting substances

         •   result in the spread of non-native invasive species, parasites or disease

         •   cause flooding from surface water


         •   cause erosion of the banks or bed of the receiving watercourse

         •   contain concrete wash water even if it has been treated

         •   contain site drainage from surface areas such as haul roads, storage or
             working areas

         •   be from a site with naturally elevated concentrations of substances

             which exceed environmental quality standards









               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Temporary de-watering from excavations to


         surface water (3)





         Before starting work on site you must:






         •   plan how to minimise the level of contaminants such as silt entering the excavation

         •   plan how to dispose of water that enters the excavation


         •   plan not to use machinery in excavations while dewatering is taking place

         •   minimise water entering the excavation, for example from rainfall, runoff, groundwater ingress or high water table

         •   consider using sustainable urban drainage construction methods





























               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Temporary de-watering from excavations to


         surface water (4)





         The discharge must not be located within, or less

         than 500 metres upstream of:






                •    Sites of Special Scientific Interest

                •    Special Areas of Conservation (SACs)

                •    Special Protection Areas (SPAs)

                •    candidate SACs, possible SACs, potential SPAs and
                     sites of community importance


                •    internationally designated Ramsar sites

                •    other nature conservation sites, such as ancient
                     woodlands, local and national nature reserves – check
                     the map


                •    local wildlife sites – find your local council













               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[How clean is clean?



























































               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Contact details











         Simon Skentelbery

         General Manager





         John F Hunt

         Regeneration Ltd



            London Road
            Grays
            Essex
            RM20 4DB


            M: 07967 306 517


            E:   simon.skentelbery@johnfhunt.co.uk
            W: johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk














               johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk                                            +44(0)1375 366 700                                       info@johnfhuntregeneration.co.uk]]></page></pages></Search>